[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 1 of 7

NETSUPPORT DNA, DATA PROTECTION,PRIVACY AND COMPLIANCE

IntroductionAs a publisher of software designed to help organisations deliver learning outcomes, we recognisethat there is an onus on us to help those organisations understand how to use the functionalityand ensure the safety and security of any personal information involved. This is no different withNetSupport DNA, our award-winning IT Asset Management and Safeguarding tool.

This document is aimed at UK/EU customers but also supports best practices and advice for otherregions (e.g., US – COPPA/FERPA). Ultimately, we hope it provides you with a betterunderstanding of where we can help you and your subsequent responsibilities.

UK/EU GDPRThe EU General Data Protection Regulation (“GDPR”) came into force across the European Unionon 25 th May 2018 and brought with it the most significant changes to data protection law in twodecades. Based on privacy by design and taking a risk-based approach, the EU GDPR has beendesigned to meet the requirements of the digital age. Subsequently, upon leaving the EU, the

Data Protection Act 2018 was updated to enact the UK GDPR, replicating the EU GDPR.

The UK GDPR aims to standardise the regulation of data protection laws and processing across theUK and work alongside the EU regulations, as well as influence other legislation across the globe –affording individuals stronger, more consistent rights to access and control of their personalinformation.

NetSupport DNA is a suite of easy-to-use tools for managing and supporting IT assets across aschoolnetwork or campus. Its features include automatic discovery of devices; hardware andsoftware inventory; change tracking and software licence management; energy monitoring; powermanagement; USB endpoint security; printer monitoring; application and internet metering; aflexible alerting suite; and an easy-to-use software distribution module. NetSupport DNA alsosupports eSafety and safeguarding with keyword and phrase monitoring to alert schools of anyonline activity that may place a student at risk; internet monitoring of websites visited; the optionfor students to report concerns directly to trusted staff; and more.

A NetSupport DNA installation processes personal data and, as such, is impacted by the GDPR.This document will provide you with all the information you need relating to NetSupport DNAto ensure that personal data is processed in accordance with the GDPR and other relevantdata protection and privacy legislations. The following sections are designed to help you withyour Record of Processing Activities, any risk assessments you may need to complete, any duediligence needed during purchase/procurement and to help you with information you mayneed for your Privacy Notice.

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 2 of 7

COPPA and FERPA compliance (USA)Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act of 1998 (COPPA) places requirements on operators ofwebsites or online services directed to children under the age of 13 years old, and on operators ofwebsites or online services that have actual knowledge that they are collecting personal informationonline from a child under the age of 13 years. The Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA)protects the privacy of student education records. It protects personally identifiable information (PII)in students’ information records from unauthorised disclosure.

NetSupport DNA fully meets the requirements for compliance as it is a fully on-premise solution. Nodata is shared with NetSupport or third-party services, and any information collected withinNetSupport DNA is solely used for the purpose of the management of devices, software and users,any activities on the devices (including where safeguarding triggers occur) and associatedoperational functions as part of support and management of IT infrastructure and Governance(remote control, AUP, etc.).the continued classes.

How does NetSupport DNA process personal data?NetSupport DNA uses an agent installed on computers to gather inventory, usage andsafeguarding data. The NetSupport DNA Agent will record the following information:HARDWARE INVENTORYThe details of which hardware inventory details are recorded are generally irrelevant to GDPRas these are not considered personal data and therefore will not be listed in this document.Exceptions to this will include where hardware information can be combined with otherinformation to create personal data (e.g. IP address, device names, groups, etc.)SOFTWARE INVENTORYAs with hardware inventory, the software inventory is not classed as personal data and istherefore not detailed in this document.USAGE INFORMATIONThe following usage information may be recorded:

• All log on, log off, lock and unlock events

• All power on, power off events

• All applications started and closed

• All websites visited

• All print jobs set to printers.SAFEGUARDING INFORMATION:When the DNA agent matches one of the configured safeguarding phrases, thefollowing information may be recorded:

• The phrase that was matched and the context it was used in (if the work was typed).

• A picture taken from the webcam, if present.

• A screenshot of the screen at the time the phrase was matched.

• A video showing the computer screen before and after the phase was matched.

• If the device has a webcam, then this can be configured to take an image of the personusing the computer.

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 3 of 7

All this information is recorded at the Agent machine, sent to the NetSupport DNA Server(using a proprietary communications protocol) and is then processed and stored in theNetSupport DNA database.

Where is the personal data stored?

NetSupport DNA is an on-premise solution and runs on servers located at the school. The datastored in NetSupport DNA is stored in an SQL server database that is either installed as part of theinstallation or a pre-existing SQL database server. Where sensitive data is stored in the NetSupportDNA database, this data is stored in an encrypted format. Where the SQL database server isinstalled as part of the NetSupport DNA installation, any direct access to the database is restrictedby the security policies built into the Microsoft SQL Server. Where a pre-existing SQL server is used,the access is controlled by the security policy in place for the pre-existing SQL server.

WHAT DATA IS COLLECTED AND STORED?The table below lists all of the personal information that is stored in the on-premise NetSupportDNA database.

Name Purpose Legal Grounds Sensitivity Collection

Name Identification Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Automatically

collected

Logon Name Identification Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Automatically

collected

Email Address Communication Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Phone Number Communication Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Mobile Phone

NumberCommunication Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Pager Number Communication Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Department Identification Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Employee/Student

NoIdentification Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Address Communication Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Optional data

Typed Phrases Safeguarding Public task /Legitimate interests\*SensitiveData

Automatically

Collected\*\*

Screen Capture Safeguarding Public task /Legitimate interests\*Sensitive Data Automatically

collected

Webcam Image Safeguarding Public task /Legitimate interests\*Sensitive Data Automatically

collected

Accessed URL Safeguarding Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Automatically

collected

Title of Accessed

URLSafeguarding Public task /Legitimate interests\*Personal Data Automatically

collected

\* The Lawful Basis for processing is decided by the Data Controller (the customer) and not by NetSupport. This table gives thesuggested basis is for public authorities/companies and other organisations respectively. Please confirm with your Data ProtectionOfficer/Data Protection lead as to the correct Lawful Basis.

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 4 of 7

\*\*Safeguarding data is automatically collected and recorded when configured to do so. This can be applied at a granular level, butonce in place the process is automatic. Resultant records would be reviewed by humans before any decisions are made, and anypriority of action/risk rating can be reconfigured to act as set out by the school.

NetSupport DNA and the GDPR data subject rightsThe GDPR defines eight rights of the individual with regard to the processing of personal data. Partof complying with the new regulations is to ensure that you can meet the terms of these individualrights. In this section, we explain each right and how it affects the NetSupport DNA product.

THE RIGHT TO BE INFORMEDIndividuals have the right to be informed about the collection and use of their personal data.This is a key transparency requirement under the GDPR. For further information and guidancesee https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-be-informed/

NetSupport DNA has an “Acceptable Use Policy” feature, and we recommend that as part ofyour Acceptable Use Policy, you should either notify users that they are being monitored andwhat data isbeing recorded or direct them to your privacy policy that should contain thisinformation.

THE RIGHT OF ACCESSUnder GDPR, individuals have the right to access their personal data. This allows individualsto be aware of and verify the lawfulness of the processing.

See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/right-of-access/

With a data subject access request, NetSupport DNA provides an export facility in thedatabase maintenance tool that can be used to export the required data.

THE RIGHT TO RECTIFICATIONUnder Article 16 of the GDPR, individuals have the right to have inaccurate personal datarectified. See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-rectification/

The NetSupport DNA Agent installed on all computers has a feature available so that any usercan view and update their personal information. Alternatively, this information can be updatedmanually by using the NetSupport DNA Console application.

THE RIGHT TO ERASUREUnder Article 17 of the GDPR, individuals have the right to have personal data erased. This isalso known as the ‘right to be forgotten’. The right is not absolute and only applies in certaincircumstances. For information on when this right is applicable, see the ICO guidance at:https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-erasure/

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 5 of 7

If this is applicable, then using the database maintenance feature from the NetSupportDNA Console, you can delete all the information related to an individual.

THE RIGHT TO RESTRICT PROCESSINGArticle 18 of the GDPR gives individuals the right to restrict the processing of their personaldata in certain circumstances. The right is not absolute, however. In most cases, you will notbe required to restrict an individual’s personal data indefinitely but will need to have therestriction in place for a certain period of time.

See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-restrict-processing/

The data that NetSupport DNA collects automatically is defined by the setting for the profilethat is active when the user is logged onto a computer. If you need to disable any collection ofdata for an individual, you can create a profile and disable all data collection; this profile canthen be assigned to an individual to stop NetSupport DNA collecting any information.

THE RIGHT TO DATA PORTABILITYThe right to data portability only applies:

• to personal data an individual has provided to a controller

• where the processing is based on the individual’s consent or for the performance of acontract

• when processing is carried out by automated means.

See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-data-portability/

This is unlikely to apply to any data processed by NetSupport DNA.

THE RIGHT TO OBJECTThe guidance from the ICO states that individuals must have an objection on ‘grounds relating tohis or her particular situation’. And that you must stop processing the personal data unless ‘youcan demonstrate compelling legitimate grounds for the processing, which override the interests,rights and freedoms of the individual’.

See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/right-to-object/

In the case of NetSupport DNA’s eSafety and safeguarding features, this would beclassed as compelling legitimate grounds for processing.

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 6 of 7

RIGHTS IN RELATION TO AUTOMATED DECISION MAKING AND PROFILINGThe GDPR has provisions on:

• automated individual decision-making (making a decision solely by automatedmeans without any human involvement); and

• profiling (automated processing of personal data to evaluate certain thingsabout an individual). Profiling can be part of an automated decision-makingprocess.

See https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation- gdpr/individual-rights/rights-related-to-automated-decision-making-including-profiling/

NetSupport DNA does not perform any decision-making based solely on automated processing.

SOME COMMON QUESTIONS

IS NETSUPPORT THE DATA PROCESSOR OR THE DATA CONTROLLER?For a customer using NetSupport DNA, NetSupport does not have access to any school’s data.Once the product is installed, all of the data is stored locally on the school’s servers. Therefore,within the context of NetSupport DNA, NetSupport is neither the data controller nor the dataprocessor.

IS THE SCHOOL THE DATA PROCESSOR OR THE DATA CONTROLLER WITHIN THE CONTEXT OFNETSUPPORT SYSTEMS?

For users of NetSupport DNA, schools remain the data controller of their own data on the system.

DOES NETSUPPORT DNA PROCESS PERSONAL DATA?Personal information associated with individual students and staff is processed by NetSupportDNA,therefore the rules of the GDPR apply to its use. This personal data is stored locally on theschool’s servers and therefore the school will remain the data controller and the dataprocessor of this personal information.

DOES NETSUPPORT DNA PROCESS SENSITIVE DATA?When an eSafety alert is triggered in NetSupport DNA, the system can be configured to recordscreen data and record images from a webcam. Due to the possible nature of this data, it couldcontain sensitive data, and as such, we recommend that this data be assumed as sensitive data.

DO I NEED TO GET CONSENT FROM ALL STAFF AND PUPILS BEFORE I CAN MONITOR THEMIN SCHOOL WITH NETSUPPORT DNA?

Generally, no – you do, however, need to give a clear notification that there is a monitoringsystem in place. This notification should explain that NetSupport DNA will record what they typeand do, so staff and pupils understand what is monitored for safeguarding purposes. Schoolsshould very clearly state why it is necessary to monitor students’ access (and, where applicable,that of staff) and how that data will be processed, stored and deleted.

[Public]

KM-194 NetSupport DNA, Data Protection, Privacy and Compliance 7 of 7

WHAT IF A CHILD/PARENT DOESN’T CONSENT TO THEM BEING MONITORED IN SCHOOL?As above, consent is generally not required. It is important to explain the need to monitorchildren in school and the reasons why. The ICO gives guidance on the lawful basis forprocessing information. See: https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-the-general-data-protection-regulation-gdpr/lawful- basis-for-processing/

The reasons will be a combination of public task (for maintained schools), legitimate interests(for independent schools) and the school’s legal or contractual obligations, including childsafety.

If you have any further questions regarding this document or any other queries regardingNetSupport DNA, please contact us:

General enquiries Sales enquiries Technical Support

+44(0)1778 382270 +44(0)1778 382270 +44(0)1778 382272press@netsupportsoftware.com sales@netsupportsoftware.com support@netsupportsoftware.com
